Welcome back to AM Northwest. You know, Oregon
art hiding in your attic or grandma's garage
could be worth some money. So here to share
some historical pieces that have value,
we welcome
antique appraiser Gary Germer. Gary,
good to see you. It's been a while.
Yeah. So when we think
about what we may find in our grandmother's
attic or around the house, let's say they want to
get
downsized, get rid of some stuff, you say you
want to keep a keen eye on paintings. Right.
Right. Paintings can be, and that's what
I brought was an array of Oregon artists,
and can be a lot of hidden treasure. I've
had several estates that we've handled
where they were worried about the china that
was worth a hundred bucks. And we have sold
paintings. One small one we recently sold for
$22,000. Wow. We're going to throw in the garage
sale. And so there could be some money.
It's worth giving it a second look.
So what are you
looking for? Well, one of the things you want to
look at, there's a lot of art that our parents
have collected or grandparents that are coming
back out on the market. And so we're going to
look at some of the paintings that they've
collected that they've collected on the market.
So these artists are getting kind of a revival
and interest for collecting on a secondary market.
What you want to do is look at it under
a loop. The number one question I get is,
is it a painting
or not? And sometimes you'll get a
Giclay, which is a print on a canvas.
Which looks very real.
Looks very real. And so you want to look for that.
Then you want to just look for an interesting
and good painting. Okay. Let's take a look at
this one and you tell me what we're seeing here.
This one here, I'm sorry. This is
William P. Hayes, a WPB artist.
in the early part of the 20th, or the middle
of the 20th century. All of these are mid-20th
century artists.
And it's a great, strong, has a lot of strong
color. This painting, interestingly enough,
when it came out of the estate,
was almost black, dirty, dark.
Oh. And it was easily cleaned. And so you
think about that when you look at a painting.
If it's dirty, that's one thing. If
the paint's peeling off the canvas,
that's another.
You can get paintings cleaned? Oh yeah. And
you should, periodically get them cleaned.
Well, it's like having your windows
not washed for 75 years. Right.
You get a different look, outlook on
the world when you wash your windows.
Absolutely. Take a look at this one in front
here and tell us what we're seeing there.
This one here? Sorry, I think. There
we go. You can see it in the monitor.
You can see the monitor.
Oh, there it is. Okay. This is William Tester
and, I'm sorry, William, Jefferson Tester,
who was married to the other small
one over here, which is Amanda Snyder.
And this is one where something that can look
really primitive actually can be surprising.
Now, when you first saw that. I thought
it was a kid's painting. Exactly.
That's what it looks
like, a kid's painting.
He did a very primitive style, but that's
about, you know, a $500 to $700 painting.
And his wife, who did little tugboats in
front, is even a more collected artist,
Amanda Snyder.
And just a small little painting of
that tugboat there is a good $1,500.
Should you, let's say you're looking at the
painting, should you then Google the artist's name?
You can Google the artist's name. There's
a number of websites like Ask Art,
artprice.com, which is a good place.
It's a good way to research it. If you get upon
a hit, there's a number of good galleries here
in Portland for Oregon artists
who specialize in Oregon artists.
And the curators there, the owners there,
out at Resale Art or Mark at Mark Humple,
are willing to share their information.
It's worth taking just an afternoon and taking
a trip and walk through their galleries.
To see what they have.
Or go online and see what they're showing online.
Let's show this. Why don't you go ahead and
hold this up to Mark and
tell us what we have here.
This is a painting by, you know,
a painter named Mark Humple.
It's a painting by Andrew Vincent, who's a
little lesser known than some of the others.
I like his work.
Yeah. It's over the McKenzie River. It's
a retail value of about $2,000 on this.
And again, it's one that is a real strong
painting, but it's also of a specific place on the
McKenzie River.
So people will collect, serious
collectors want things from their area.
So someone along the river would
love to have a painting like that.
Of course. That makes sense.
What has been the biggest find you've ever
found in, when it comes to an artwork?
Personally, you hear these stories all
the time of the hundreds of thousands.
I've yet to hit that.
One painting, it was actually, it
turned out to be a British artist.
But it was extremely dirty of two little
girls. The painting was dirty, not the girls.
Right.
But the painting was really dirty and we saw
that the paint was solid, could be cleaned.
And we got it for $200 and I had it
cleaned and sold in New York for $38,000.
Oh, wow. Okay.
So my daughter went to a
better college than she was.
That's what we initially chailed it for.
That's funny. Tell us about this one.
Charles Haney was very prolific,
but also very, is a very popular.
And you'll find him in both nice oils,
watercolors, he did a lot of different mediums,
and black and white etchings.
And so in descending order, the paintings
can go for, you know, into the thousands,
the smaller ones, you know, 900 to
1,000-inch portraits and stuff that he did.
And then this one here.
Well, these two are black and white etchings
and I wanted to emphasize the idea that a black
and white etching shouldn't be dismissed.
This one here is Gilkey. You can probably
hear the Gilkey Art Center at the art museum.
And that's what's named after his
collection, helped found that.
And you can find that. And when it's an artist-made
print, it will be actually signed in pencil
by the artist.
And that lets you know the artist was
actually in the room making the print.
And isn't there usually a number
as to how many prints were made?
Oftentimes that's true, and on the smaller
Knapp one there, you'll see it's one of five.
So one of five, and see,
they only made five.
So it makes it truly a limited. Now,
this one does not have that number.
So this was what they called an open edition,
meaning he made them and then he could have made
more.
There is an undetermined number,
but a limited one helps it.
And that's truly a limited. It kind of became in
the 80s, the idea of limited edition of everything.
But it would be thousands and
they're really not valuable.
That's not very limited. Lastly, let's take
a look at this one. Tell me what we're...
I love Percy Mancer. Percy Mancer really caught
a lot of Oregon, did a lot of Oregon landscapes.
He was an illustrator, but he
is one of the most popular.
And really caught the early 20th
century of the Oregon farm scene.
And this one is worth probably
in the $3,000 to $4,000 range.
Okay, really good tips, Gary. We're going to
put the information on our website at K2.com.
Good to see you again.
Thank you. Have a good one.